<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay on ecclesiastical authority in which the pretence of an independent power in the church, to a divine right in the election of bishops; to the invalidity of lay deprivations; to the inseparable relation of a bishop to his see; to an obligation of continuing communion with the deprived bishops; and several other things relating to the nonjurors separation from our church, are particulary and impartially examined. By John Turner, D.D. Vicar of Greenwich, and chaplain to His Royal Highness the Prince.</title>
            <author>Turner, John, 1660-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617-1717</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14037</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102040</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837841</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2187</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14037)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2187)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1040:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay on ecclesiastical authority in which the pretence of an independent power in the church, to a divine right in the election of bishops; to the invalidity of lay deprivations; to the inseparable relation of a bishop to his see; to an obligation of continuing communion with the deprived bishops; and several other things relating to the nonjurors separation from our church, are particulary and impartially examined. By John Turner, D.D. Vicar of Greenwich, and chaplain to His Royal Highness the Prince.</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, 1660-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 77, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wyat, at the Rose in St. Paul's church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617 [i.e. 1717?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identicial records exists in ESTC on basis that imprint is misprinted, and is really 1717. Erroneously included in STC on basis of misprinted date.</note>
                  <note>Errata on verso of L4, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; Pages 37-8 (leaf F3) lacking.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Sion College. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Temporal power --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Nonjurors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2187:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2187:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY ON <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Authority:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which the Pretence of an <hi>Independent Power</hi> in the CHURCH, to a <hi>Divine Right</hi> in the <hi>Election</hi> of <hi>Biſhops;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Invalidity of <hi>Lay Deprivations;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Inſeparable Relation of a BISHOP to his See;</p>
            <p>To an Obligation of continuing Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the <hi>Deprived Biſhops;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeveral other Things relating to the <hi>Nonjurors</hi> Separation from our CHURCH, are particularly and impartially Examined.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOHN TURNER, <hi>D. D.</hi> Vicar of <hi>Greenwich,</hi> and Chaplain to His Royal Highneſs the PRINCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON: Printed for</hi> JOHN WYAT, <hi>at the</hi> Roſe <hi>in St.</hi> Paul's Church-yard. 1617.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:2187:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2187:2"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY ON <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Authority.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE many irregular and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Practices of the Romiſh Clergy under the Pretence of an exempt Juriſdiction, and an Authority <hi>Independent</hi> on the Civil Power; cauſed the Governors of our CHURCH to take that Doctrine into their ſerious Conſideration, at the Beginning of our REFORMATION; and in our XXXVII<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Article</hi> they have determined and ſettled it thus: That <hi>the Queen's Majeſty,</hi> for this was done in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Time, <hi>hath the chief Power in this Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and all other her Dominions; unto whom the chief</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2187:3"/> 
               <hi>Government of all Eſtates of this Realm whether they be Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, in all Cauſes doth appertain.</hi> And then to avoid Offence, and prevent Miſconſtructions, as the Queen had declared in her Injunctions, ſo the ſaid <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle,</hi> thus explains the forementioned Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. <hi>We give not</hi> hereby <hi>to our Princes the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring either of God's Word, or of the Sacraments; but only that Prerogative which we ſee to have been given always to all godly Princes in Holy Scripture by God Himſelf; that they ſhould rule all Eſtates and Degrees</hi> of Men <hi>committed to their Charge by God, whether they be Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or Temporal.</hi> And this was ſo confirmed by the Canons in the Beginning of King <hi>James</hi> I's Reign, that if the Authority of our CHURCH might be admitted to be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive in this Matter, we ſee plainly what that was, and is. But the giving ſo much Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to Princes over <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Perſons</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes and Affairs,</hi> is complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of by ſome among us as an Encroachment, and a dangerous Compliance; an <hi>enſlaving Principle,</hi> which controuls the Powers of the CHURCH, that, as they ſay, ought to be exempt and Independent.</p>
            <p>THIS Point then, not being ſucceſsfully enough determined by the declared Judgment of our CHURCH in Her <hi>Articles</hi> and <hi>Canons;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2187:3"/> muſt, it ſeems, be brought under a farther Examination. And it muſt be conſidered not only as a Subject of Debate and Speculation, but, at this Time, it is become a Matter of the greateſt Moment and Importance to our Peace both in CHURCH and STATE. All the Enemies of the late happy REVOLU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, are gone into the Defence of that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Authority;</hi> to ſay no more. And all thoſe other Notions and Opinions whereby the <hi>Non-jurors</hi> would vindicate their Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Communion of our CHURCH, are built upon this Foundation. And it will not be eaſy to make them ſenſible, that this their Separation is Unjuſtifiable and Wrong, if this Claim be allowed good. On the other Hand, if it can be proved, That the CHURCH has no ſuch exempt, and independent Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as is pretended; we ſhall ſtrike at the very Root of their untoward Principles and Proceedings. In our Inquiry into this Matter,</p>
            <p n="1">1. THE firſt Thing that occurs to our Obſervation, is, That the STATE is found in the actual and full Poſſeſſion of Authority over all their Subjects, and in all Affairs whatſoever, antecedently to the CHURCH'S Claim. We are not born Prieſts, as we are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2187:4"/> born Subjects; but are made ſuch upon a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Maturity of Age; and are therefore to conſider what Share of Authority the Prince loſes over any of his Subjects upon their Admiſſion into Holy Orders; and what is the Foundation of the pretended Change. And as to this, we ſhall ſoon be ſenſible,</p>
            <p n="2">2. THAT there is Nothing in <hi>natural</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to be pleaded as the Ground of ſuch an Exemption or Independency. For accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that, Kings had a Right to the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood alſo, and were the undoubted ſupreme Judges and Determiners of all Affairs. <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech</hi> and <hi>Jethro,</hi> we all know, were ſuch. Nor does it appear, that there ever was any Separation of the Eccleſiaſtical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from the Temporal, before the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaic</hi> Diſpenſation, which was a Type of the Evangelical; and conſequently no Room for any Debates or Diſputes of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the firſt Natural State of Mankind. It muſt therefore all be laid in Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation and Inſtitution. From whence I think it plainly follows,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly.</hi> THAT if the CHURCH has any Right to ſuch an exempt and indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Authority as is now pleaded for, it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2187:4"/> muſt be founded on that Divine Commiſſion which CHRIST gave to his Apoſtles and their Succeſſors, and by them to his CHURCH to the End of the World. The Way then to know what there is to be ſaid for ſuch a Claim, is, to conſider well the Contents of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion which muſt be looked on as the great Charter of the Goſpel, upon which all Her appropriated Rights and Privileges, Her Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Powers, Her Immunities and Franchiſes are built. The Subſtance then of CHRIST'S Commiſſion to his Apoſtles was, That they ſhould <hi>make Proſelytes of all Nations</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. xxviii. 19, 20. Joh. xx. 21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> by <hi>Preaching God's Word;</hi> that they ſhould <hi>Baptize them,</hi> and by that Sacrament admit them into <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Church;</hi> that they ſhould afterwards inſtruct and train them up in the Pure Chriſtian Worſhip and Holineſs, and in that Worſhip commemorate CHRIST'S Death in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> according to his Inſtitution; <hi>bind</hi> Offenders, <hi>looſe</hi> Penitents, and by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining Miniſters make an effectual Proviſion for the perpetual Continuance of this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry which CHRIST has thus committed to 'em, <hi>to the End of the World,</hi> according to his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment. So that <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Performing Divine Service</hi> in the Worſhip of GOD; <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring</hi> the <hi>Sacraments;</hi> inflicting <hi>Cenſures,</hi> and paſſing <hi>Sentence</hi> upon enormous Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2187:5"/> 
               <hi>Abſolving</hi> the Penitent from ſuch Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and <hi>Ordaining</hi> Miniſters. Theſe and whatever other Particulars of Miniſtration in the Divine Offices of Religion, are by the ſpecial Commiſſion of CHRIST in any Part of it appropriated to the Spiritual Governors of the CHURCH, become thereby, the Peculiar ſacred Powers of the Chriſtian Prieſthood. Concerning all which it is allow'd and grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 1. That the CHURCH does not derive Her Authority to the Execution of them from any Temporal Powers or Potentates; but from JESUS CHRIST alone by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Divine Commiſſion. 2. That as they were not originally derived from, ſo neither can they be taken away, or made to ceaſe by any ſecular Authorities whatſoever. 3. That neither can any ſecular Powers of themſelves execute theſe Divine and Holy Offices. The very End and Reaſon of taking theſe Holy Offices out of the Hands of the ſecular Powers, who before had executed them, and of veſting them in a diſtinct Set or Order of Men, ſtill requires that they ſhould continue ſo ſeparated. And conſequently, all the Powers ſpecify'd in CHRIST'S Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, are the limitted and <hi>appropriated Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> which belong to the Spiritual Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of the CHURCH alone; and which no
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2187:5"/> Temporal Potentates can take upon them to execute, without breaking in upon CHRIST'S Inſtitution, and ſubverting the very Ends and Reaſons of their original Separation. And therefore, if no more had been intended by the <hi>Independent Authority</hi> of CHRIST'S Church in the Execution of their Prieſtly Office than this, That they who derived not this Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the State, could not have it taken away by them; and that the ſecular Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are by CHRIST'S Commiſſion excluded from the Performance of all the Divine Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices ſpecify'd in it: The <hi>Church of England</hi> has declared Her Judgment in Favour of ſuch a Claim; and we ſhould have entred into no Diſputes againſt it.</p>
            <p>BUT then, he who himſelf has no Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to baptize, may yet be a <hi>competent Judge</hi> of the Care and Fidelity of thoſe who do. And he who has no Power to adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Lord's-Supper,</hi> or to ordain Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, may yet be capable of taking Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of the Neglects, and of the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages committed in thoſe Performances. So that it is one Thing to miniſter in the Holy Offices and Service of the Church; and another to have Rule and Government, and a judicial Cognizance of the Care, Fidelity, and good or evil Conduct of thoſe who do. This leads me to conſider,</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2187:6"/>
            <p> 2. THAT beſides the <hi>Miniſtration</hi> in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Offices, the Power of the <hi>Keys</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> there are other Powers and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities claimed by the Church: Such are all the General Powers of Government, of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling in Synods, of Conſulting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on important Occaſions, of making Laws or Canons; of appointing to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches or Diſtricts their proper Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors; of determining religious Debates and Diſputes; of preſcribing Rules of Order and Diſcipline, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which, as not being expreſsly mentioned in, or <hi>appropriated</hi> by CHRIST'S Commiſſion as the other divine Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Religion are, can belong to the Church only of <hi>Common-Right,</hi> as it is a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; and as ſuch Acts of Government are the conſtant and <hi>common Rights</hi> of every Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Community.</p>
            <p>A SOCIETY cannot ſubſiſt without Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; as therefore the Chriſtian Church is by CHRIST'S Commiſſion conſtituted a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Society there is no Doubt, but that it thereby obtains a certain Right to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of all ſuch Authority in Government as other Eſtabliſhed Communities are uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſs'd of.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2187:6"/>
            <p> THE Queſtion then is, not whether the Church has a Right to the Exerciſe of ſuch Authority, for it is undeniably evident that ſhe has: But what is the Foundation of that Authority, and how far it will hold good to the Excluſion of the ſecular Powers. Now unleſs it could be made appear that theſe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of Government are by CHRIST'S Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſpecify'd and appropriated to the Prieſthood as the divine Offices of its Holy Miniſtration are: There can be no other Reaſon or Ground of this Claim than that of <hi>common Right</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> to the Support of this ſpiritual Community and to the Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great End for which it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</p>
            <p>WE ſee therefore that in this Controverſy a great regard is to be had to the Diſtinction here made between the divine Offices of the Chriſtian Prieſthood and the more General Powers of Government. The former are allow'd to be <hi>appropriated</hi> to the Orders of the Biſhops and Clergy only. The latter are thoſe Powers and Authorities which our preſent Controverſies and Diſſentions are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. And if I am right in Stating the CHURCH'S Claim and Title thereto, I ſhall certainly be Right in the Determination of this diſpute. So far as they are <hi>Neceſſary</hi> to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2187:7"/> due Execution of CHRIST'S Commiſſion, the CHURCH has undoubted Right thereto. And if Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi> and his Friends had gone no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in claiming a Right to the Exerciſe of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Authority Independently on the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> than as that ſhall be found <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the Propagation and Eſtabliſhment of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; I am apt to think that all Chriſtians would have come into it. I for my Part, can make no Scruple to affirm, that by Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Chriſts Commiſſion to his Apoſtles and their Succeſſors to <hi>Preach</hi> and Propagate the Goſpel, and to <hi>gather Him a Church</hi> thereby: They have an undoubted Right and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to do every Thing in the Exerciſe of their Spiritual Offices, which ſhall be found <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the Support of the Chriſtian Faith and CHURCH. But if Men will not content themſelves with this, without going farther; if they will claim an Univerſal Inherent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of doing every Thing in Matters of Religion, if they pleaſe, by themſelves; and to be the ſole Proper and Rightful Judges of all Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, and Matters; with a divine Right to exclude the Secular Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity at their Pleaſure, and to make <hi>Null</hi> and <hi>Invalid</hi> every Thing that is done by the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Powers in theſe Affairs without the Clergy's Approbation and Conſent: This I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2187:7"/> think a moſt Unreaſonable and Unrighteous Demand; and I have theſe ſix Things to plead againſt it.</p>
            <p>I. SUCH a Claim ſeems contrary to the very Nature of the Powers that we are now reaſoning about. They are not the peculiar <hi>appropriated</hi> Offices of the Prieſthood, ſuch as <hi>Miniſtring</hi> in the Divine Service, adminiſtring Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which we have already owned Kings and Princes to be excluded from; But they are the CHURCH'S common Powers of Government which belong to Her only of common Right, and to the General Exerciſe of which other Societies are entitled as well as the CHURCH. Now theſe general Powers of Government are no otherwiſe to be exercis'd <hi>excluſive</hi> of and <hi>Independently</hi> on the Secular Authority, than the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of Affairs requires them ſo to be. And that Authority which has no other Reaſon or Foundation then its <hi>Uſefulneſs</hi> or <hi>Neceſſity</hi> as a <hi>Means</hi> to the attaining to ſuch an End, certainly loſes a great deal of its Force and Obligation in all thoſe Inſtances in which it ceaſes to be uſeful or neceſſary, and where the End may be as effectually obtained without it. And this is the true Reaſon of all that Difference which is obſervable in Hiſtory in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2187:8"/> the Practice of the Biſhops and Governours of the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> in the Exerciſe of theſe very Powers under Heathen and under Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperors and Governours. When their Heathen Governours caſt them off and left them to themſelves, they then manag'd all Things by themſelves, the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of their Affairs requiring that they ſhould ſo do. But when the Chriſtian Emperors took the Affairs of Chriſtians into their Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, and made Laws, and paſſed Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and executed Judgment therein: The Chriſtian Biſhops and Clergy unanimouſly gave Way, and very readily ſubmitted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            <p>IT may poſſibly have ſome weight with ſome of my Readers to obſerve, that even Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi> in the Collection of Papers late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Publiſhed by his Friends, and which were Written and Publiſhed on purpoſe to carry up the Powers of the Prieſthood, and an <hi>Independent Authority</hi> as high as poſſibly he could: Yet comes in to this Diſtinction of the CHURCH'S Communicable and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable Authority. Whatever indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Ends he might have to ſerve in his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to Support the Spiritual Authority of the Nonjuring Deprived Biſhops: Yet he was too well acquainted with Primitive
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2187:8"/> Church Hiſtory to think, that all the <hi>Chriſtian Churches</hi> Authorities are alike exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the Secular Powers. And accordingly as I find him quoted <hi>p.</hi> 27. he allows; <hi>that the Church on</hi> valuable <hi>Conſiderations may in ſome Caſes modify the Exerciſe of Her Juſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and make Grants and Conceſſions to the State.</hi> Pray mind that, for if Princes and States may on any Conſiderations be admitted to a ſhare of the <hi>Churches Juſt Power:</hi> Then it is plain and evident that in ſuch Caſes it is not JESUS CHRIST, that by his Divine Laws excludes them, but theſe Church-Men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But let us ſee what Inſtances of this kind he mentions, and they are ſuch as theſe; That the CHURCH ſhall conſent not <hi>to call Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods without acquainting the King,</hi> and <hi>obtaining his Leave if Poſſible; not to make Foreigners, or Clerks of a Foreign Allegiance Biſhops; to make no Biſhops but what ſhall be ſuppoſed worthy of the Kings Nomination; to give the Builders and Endowers of Churches the Honour and Privelege of preſenting worthy Clerks to ſupply the Cure of them;</hi> and <hi>Noblemen to Erect Chapels, and to chooſe Chaplains for their Families.</hi> There are then it ſeems Caſes and Conſiderations, in and upon which, notwithſtanding all the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Powers of the CHURCH, Kings may have <hi>Authority,</hi> in <hi>calling Synods,</hi> in <hi>Nominating</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2187:9"/> 
               <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and in the <hi>Preſentation of Clerks to the Cure of Souls.</hi> Here I would ask in what Caſes, and upon what Conſiderations any of theſe Kings or Nobles may be allowed to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Sacraments and Ordain Miniſters? I know that this will not be allow'd at all by any Means, or on any Conſiderations what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. It ſeems then, that in Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi>'s own Opinion, altho' ſome of the Powers of the CHURCH are Excluſive and Uncommunicable to Lay Hands: Yet others they may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to a ſhare of, if the Conſideration be but good, and the Authority not abuſed. Now I would willingly know, what is the true Foundation of this Difference, which Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi> himſelf admits of? I would have it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly declared, whether CHRIST'S Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on has Appropriated theſe Powers to the CHURCH which may be ſo <hi>modified,</hi> and has Excluded Secular Potentates from them, or on what foot that <hi>Modifications</hi> ſtands. And at the ſame time let them add, why the Influence of the Civil Magiſtrates Authority to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Peace and Safety, and good Order of a Kingdom, may not be allowed as juſt a Conſideration and as good a Reaſon of his Exerciſing Authority in ſuch affairs, as any munificent act of Beneficence or Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2187:9"/>
            <p> BUT to bring this Debate with Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi> and his Friends to a Short Iſſue; Either JESUS CHRIST by his Goſpel, and his Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to his Apoſtles has Appropriated all Eccleſiaſtical Authoritty to the Clergy only, and Excluded the Secular Power from it, or he has not. If he has, and the Certainty of that be made appear, then they ought on no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whatſoever to be allowed any Share therein, becauſe that is acting contrary to CHRIST'S Commiſſion and Laws. But if he has not, then the CHURCH has no Divine Right at all of Excluding their Authority and acting Independently. The Conſequence of this is plain and undeniable. For to Exclude the Juriſdiction of the Secular Powers where CHRIST by his Divine Commiſſion has not Excluded them, is to do it without Reaſon and contrary to Juſtice.</p>
            <p>But that which Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi> and his Friends lay the greateſt Streſs upon is; 1. The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Society; and, 2. The Powers by which it Subſiſted in the Beginning.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the Nature of the Society they tell us that it is CHRIST'S <hi>Spiritual Kingdom or</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Non-Juring Church. <hi>prop.</hi> I. II.</note> 
               <hi>Incorporation, which had a Being Independent on the Secular Power for above three hundred years before the Government of it was interwoven with</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2187:10"/> 
               <hi>the ſecular Government and Laws.</hi> I grant all this to be true; but becauſe there ſeems to be great Streſs laid on this <hi>Independency</hi> ſo much talked of; I deſire that it may be conſidered what it means. For in a Chriſtian Country, the CHURCH and STATE are not two Diſtinct Societies like the Kingdoms of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> made up of different People and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects inhabiting different Territories: but are One and the ſame Body of Men conſidered in two different Relations and Capacities. The ſame Perſons are at once Members of the Church and Subjects of the State, and ſo conſtitute but One Society of Men under two capacities of Government.</p>
            <p>AND Even in this twofold Capacity their Affairs, their Duties and Obligations are ſo mixt and interwoven, that in a Chriſtian State it is ſcarce Practicable for the Church to Govern and Manage her ſpiritual Affairs without influencing and affecting the State. Nay in the Extent of <hi>ſpiritual Power</hi> now claimed, it is abſolutely impoſſible ſo to do. So that this Conteſt for an Independent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the Government of the Church, is nothing elſe but a Struggle to take the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of Religion and all religious Affairs out of the Hands of Kings and Princes. And if they once do this, the STATE muſt be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2187:10"/> brought to depend upon the CHURCH, becauſe the CHURCH will be independent on the STATE; and ſo it would be in a very fine Condition. In ſhort, while ſuch a Power is contended for, the CHURCH and STATE muſt inevitably claſh and diſagree, and there is no Way to conſult and ſecure the publick Peace, without a Subordination of the one to the other in their Adminiſtration of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>AND as to the CHURCH'S having a <hi>Being independent on the ſecular Power for the firſt three hundred Years:</hi> it proceeded only from the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of her Circumſtances and Affairs at that Time, that She acted independently on the ſecular Potentates. It was when Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity was in a State of Perſecution, and the ſecular Powers refuſed to intermeddle in Her Government. Then, it is very true, that She ſubſisted of Herſelf; and this proves undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, that the CHURCH has a Capacity ſo to do when Need requires. But it does not prove, that it is a deſirable Thing for Her to be in ſuch a Caſe; or that She has a Divine Right and Power to exclude the ſecular Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, if they think fit to interpoſe their Authority. But I ſhall ſpeak more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to this hereafter. I am now only ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what weak and inſufficient Reaſons Men
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2187:11"/> allege for an Independent Authority in the Church; of which, I think, this is a very great Inſtance; that becauſe She did once ſo ſubſiſt out of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> therefore She muſt always do ſo, out of <hi>Choice,</hi> or has a <hi>Divine Right</hi> ſo to do, when ever She pleaſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. BUT they tell us, That this <hi>Spiritual Kingdom of</hi> CHRIST, is alſo <hi>a Royal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, a Kingdom of Prieſts, the chief Prieſts</hi> of which are <hi>Regal Prieſts, or Kings, as well as</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. ii. 9. Prop. 18. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Prieſts unto God.</hi> That <hi>their Government in their ſeveral Dioceſes or Diſtricts, is Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal;</hi> and <hi>the Biſhops are therein the ſupreme Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>his Legates,</hi> or <hi>Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents,</hi> in regard to whom, <hi>Chriſtian Emperors and Kings are their ſpiritual Subjects and Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors,</hi> and ought to <hi>be obedient to them.</hi> All theſe high Titles, and big Words, are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently intended to poſſeſs the People with a Notion, that Kings and Princes muſt have Nothing to do with Biſhops, unleſs it be when the CHURCH, in <hi>Conſideration</hi> of ſome valuable Advantages and temporal Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, will <hi>modify Her Power,</hi> and indulge them in a Share in Government on their good Behaviour. In any other Caſe, it is ſacred; <hi>favete linguis, ite Profani,</hi> ſay not a Word of Juriſdiction or Authority; be gone, it is the <hi>Ark of</hi> GOD, touch it not, leſt you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2187:11"/> die. Now in anſwer to all theſe high Strains, for the Satisfaction of modeſt, ſober, chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Minds, let us enquire,</p>
            <p n="1">1. WHAT St. <hi>Peter</hi> means, when he tells us of all Chriſtians; for he does not ſpeak of the Governors of the Church alone, but of the whole Community of Chriſtian Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers; when he ſays, <hi>Ye are a Royal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. ii. 9.</note> In the fourth Verſe of that Chapter, he vindicates CHRIST himſelf from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt that Unbelievers had poured out upon Him; and he calls Him, <hi>a living Stone, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowed indeed of Men, but choſen of</hi> GOD, <hi>and precious.</hi> And then, for their farther Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation under the Reproaches that were thrown upon themſelves for Believing in Him, he adds. <hi>Verſe</hi> 6. <hi>Ye alſo, as living Stones are built up a ſpiritual Houſe, an holy Prieſthood, to offer up ſpiritual Sacrifices, accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God by Jeſus Christ.</hi> And again, ver. 9. <hi>Ye are a choſen Generation, a</hi> ROYAL PRIESTHOOD, <hi>an holy Nation, a</hi> PECULIAR PEOPLE, <hi>that ye ſhould ſhew forth the Praiſes of Him, who hath called you out of Darkneſs into his marvellous Light.</hi> Whatever, therefore, might be intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that Expreſſion under the Jewiſh Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation when it was firſt uſed, it is plain, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> intended no more by it, than
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2187:12"/> to ſet forth how honourable and favourable a State all Chriſtian People are in with GOD, whom He loves and eſteems, and counts dear to Him, even as the Prieſts of His Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And what is all this to the making Biſhops <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> and Lords of the Flock of CHRIST, with a <hi>Supremacy of Power?</hi> Not but that I readily allow, that the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which CHRIST firſt committed to his Apoſtles, was by them put into the Hands of Biſhops; and by them is convey'd down to us; and that they are under CHRIST the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governours of this ſpiritual Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, whenever the ſecular Potentates refuſe to concern themſelves therein. And very great Deference, Regard, Honour and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ought to be paid to them all on that Account.</p>
            <p>AND yet, methinks, this high Style, and lofty Language, does not mighty well ſuit the meek, modeſt Temper of the Goſpel, in that there is not much of this grand Strain in the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> The <hi>Royal Prieſthood,</hi> we have ſeen, will do them but little Service, in that it reſpects every private Chriſtian, as well as the <hi>ſpiritual Governors</hi> of the CHURCH. And altho' we are call'd <hi>Ambaſſadours of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Stewards of the Myſteries of God;</hi> yet this <note place="margin">2 Cor. i. 24.</note> our Chriſtian Embaſſy muſt be managed with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2187:12"/> all imaginable Meekneſs and Humility. St. <hi>Paul</hi> after a very ſmall degree of Authority in threat'ning the Corinthians corrects himſelf thus; <hi>Not that we have Dominion over your Faith.</hi> And St. <hi>Peter</hi> very affectionately exhorts <note place="margin">1 Pet. v. 3.</note> the Clergy, not to carry themſelves <hi>as being Lords over Gods Heritage, but Examples to the Flock.</hi> But Dr. <hi>Hickes,</hi> and his <hi>Non-juring</hi> Friends, are for <hi>lording</hi> it over <hi>Emperors and Kings,</hi> their <hi>ſpiritual Inferiors</hi> and <hi>Subjects,</hi> who ought to be <hi>obedient</hi> to the Biſhops and Clergy in what concerns Religion. Not ſo the Meek, the Bleſſed, and Humble JESUS, who teaches his Apoſtles thus: <hi>The Kings of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke xxii. 26.</note> 
               <hi>the Gentiles exerciſe Lordſhip over them; but it ſhall not be ſo with you. But he that is greateſt among you, let him be as the younger; and he that is chief, as he that doth ſerve.</hi> We may ſee in the Style we uſe, what Manner of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit we are of; and how far we are degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Original Meekneſs of our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Religion. And yet at laſt, after all this great Talk, if it does not infect the Minds of the ignorant, common People, it is nothing to the Purpoſe. For when all is ſaid, that can be ſaid this Way, the main Queſtion ſtill remains to be argu'd; which is,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2187:13"/> 2. WHETHER all the Fullneſs of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which the Clergy can be ſuppoſed to have in the ſpiritual Affairs of the CHURCH, does amount to an Excluſion of the ſupreme Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and Authority of the STATE? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther CHRIST ever intended that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church ſhould be ſo managed by <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Men alone, the Biſhops and Paſtors of it, as that the <hi>ſupreme ſecular Powers</hi> ſhould have no Right or Title to any Judicial Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority therein; but be excluded from that, as well as from the Divine Offices of the Prieſthood? And the Determination of this Matter, muſt not be made by any high Strains of Rhetoric, or lofty, metaphorical Titles that may be uſed; but from the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and Authority that are really given and <hi>appropriated</hi> to them in Holy Scriptures. So that unleſs it could be proved from thence, that the general <hi>Powers</hi> of <hi>governing</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> are by CHRIST'S Commiſſion <hi>appropriated</hi> to the Prieſthood as the <hi>Miniſtration</hi> in Holy Offices is; all the reſt that can be ſaid, will be to no Purpoſe. For it muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and unjuſt to exclude the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of ſecular Powers, where GOD and CHRIST have not excluded them. To this Argument, let me add,</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2187:13"/>
            <p> II. THAT ſuch an exempt, <hi>independent,</hi> excluſive Authority in the CHURCH, where it is not highly neceſſary to the Support of Religion, is indeed very abſurd. It has Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worſe in it than erecting <hi>Imperium in Imperio;</hi> it is actually ſetting up the Kingdom of God the SON, in Oppoſition to that of the FATHER, and in Derogation of His ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority and Power.</p>
            <p>DR. <hi>Hickes</hi> and his Friends tell us, That the Chriſtian CHURCH is the <hi>ſpiritual King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Body of Chriſt.</hi> I grant this to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true; and ſo is the Government of the whole World, by the temporal Powers of it, the Temporal Kingdom of God the FATHER, <hi>Who is Lord of all the Earth,</hi> the <hi>only Potentate,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joſh. iii. 11, 13.</note> the <hi>King Eternal; whoſe Kingdom is an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom, and ruleth over all.</hi> In this Kingdom the Civil Powers are <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> for the Good of Mankind; they are the <hi>Miniſters of God for Good,</hi> to whom all <note place="margin">1 Tim. vi. 15, &amp; i. 17. Pſal. cxlv. 13.—ciii. 19. Rom. xiii. 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>muſt needs be ſubject for Conſcience Sake.</hi> And therefore for the Miniſters of CHRIST to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and lord it over the Miniſters of GOD the FATHER, is to invert the ſacred Order of Things, and to forget the Subordination of the SON to the FATHER.</p>
            <p>GOD, for the Honour of the ever bleſſed Redeemer, was pleaſed to grant Him a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2187:14"/> within his own Dominions, with Rule and Power over <hi>all Mankind</hi> in order to our Salvation; and to the effectual Eſtabliſhment of it, to appoint Him <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of his own; and to take away from tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Governours the Miniſtration of thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, and ſacred Offices which they before performed. But as it does not appear by CHRIST'S Commiſſion, that He has appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated all the Powers of Government in his CHURCH, to the Biſhops and Clergy only, together with the Authority of thoſe ſacred Miniſtrations; it is certainly very wrong in them to aſſume a Power of excluding uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally the Authority of the FATHER'S Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry. The Diſpenſation of the SON, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Excellent and Glorious, as bleſſed be GOD, it is, ought yet certainly to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in Subordination to that of the FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER. And to pretend the contrary, muſt needs be very abſutd and diſpleaſing to Them both.</p>
            <p>AND yet this Abſurdity, as great as it is, is carry'd ſtill farther; and the Abettors of it not content with the Claim of an <hi>independent</hi> Power only, plead for a <hi>ſuperior</hi> Authority in the Church; becauſe that is <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and extends to the Souls of Men. This is not only in Effect to deny the Civil Magiſtrates
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2187:14"/> Concern in Matters of Religion, and where the Souls of Men are affected: But more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, it is to ſet up the SON <hi>above</hi> the FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER, by making the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the SON <hi>ſuperior</hi> to that of the FATHER. This is what I cannot but think unreaſonable, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Deſign and Intention of Them both. It is under the Favour and Protection of the SON, to reject the Authority and Supremacy of the FATHER; than which ſcarce any thing can be more offenſive to him. To this let me add,</p>
            <p>III. THAT the true Kingdom of GOD, and the Religion of JESUS CHRIST eſtabliſhed therein do not appear to be at all more ſtrong and ſafe, and ſecure from Corruptions by ſuch an Independent Authority than they would be otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>REMEMBER we are here diſputing only about an <hi>independent Power</hi> in the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church, and the Management of its Affairs for the Succeſs of Religion. It would therefore, methinks, be much in Favour of ſuch a Pretenſion, if it could be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by long Experience throughout all Ages, that the Purity of this Holy Religion had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been better ſecured that Way than the other. And that it had as conſtantly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2187:15"/> when ever it was brought under the Direction and Juriſdiction of the STATE. But alas! this was true only in the firſt Ages of Chriſtianity, when the Governors of the Church had more extraordinary and miraculous Aſſiſtances from the Holy Ghoſt. Then indeed, the Purity of Religion was effectually preſerved, and the Word of GOD <hi>mightily grew and prevailed.</hi> But when the eſſential Principles and Laws of Chriſtianity were committed to Writing, and the Clergy were to gain ſpiritual Knowledge by Reading them; when the extraordinary Powers of the Holy Ghoſt began to be removed, and Men were aſiſted, as they are now, only by the ordinary Influences thereof; and in Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of this, the ſpiritual Governors of the Church were ſubject to the ſame Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and Infirmities, and Temptations as other Men now a-days are: Religion ſoon felt the Fruits of this, and its genuine Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſoon began to decay, and declined apace. Till by Degrees it grew ſo corrupt that to uſe St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words, on a like Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>The whole Creation groaned and travailed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. viii. 21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>in Pain together, waiting to be delivered from this Bondage of Corruption, into the glorious Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2187:15"/>
            <p> So that whatever Advantages Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty received by the pure Faith, and conſtant Patience, by the great Integrity and Piety of the Primitive Chriſtians in the <hi>three firſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies;</hi> it ſuffered at leaſt as much in after-Ages, by the evil Conduct of thoſe who were in Poſſeſſion of thoſe Spiritual Powers. To give one notorious Inſtance of this; I would deſire theſe learned Gentlemen to read the Hiſtory and Acts of the ſecond Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and there to conſider by whoſe Over-bearing Authority the Idolatry of Image-worſhip was firſt brought into the Church of CHRIST. Such Inſtances ſhew too plainly that the true Advancement of CHRIST'S Spiritual Kingdom, depends more upon the <hi>Fidelity</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> of its Miniſters, than upon the <hi>regal, independent, Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IF therefore the <hi>Non-jurors,</hi> in Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their <hi>Schiſm,</hi> had not contracted an Habit of Writing Paradoxes, One would won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mightily to hear them impute the <hi>Atheiſm Deiſm, Hereſy, Schiſms, Infidelity, Profaneneſs,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Hick. Collect. <hi>pag.</hi> 29.</note> 
               <hi>and Immorality, that are found in this Land,</hi> to the taking away of this ſupreme, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Power of the Church. Let any Man look Abroad into <hi>Italy, Spain</hi> or <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> there he will find the Government of the Church in the Hands of thoſe very Men,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2187:16"/> whoſe Right to it Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi> contends for; and that too, with greater Immunities and Exemptions than he has pleaded for. And yet in all theſe Kingdoms, he will find as much Infidelity and Irreligion, as ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Vice, and Immorality, and Profaneneſs, as in any Part of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> Only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps with a little more Reſerve for Fear of an <hi>Inquiſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN ſhort, That our Diſcipline is too much loſt, we all complain, as well as the <hi>Non-jurors.</hi> But that the Matter would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be mended, by putting it wholly into the Hands of the Clergy with an <hi>independent</hi> and unreſtrained Authority, is what cannot be allowed: Becauſe where the Church has that Power, Religion is more infamouſly corrupted than in any other Places of the Chriſtian World.</p>
            <p>LET us but reflect what Oppoſition the Reformation of it met with here at Home, from thoſe very Men whoſe independent Power is now pleaded for. And with how much Difficulty it was reſcued out of their Hands, that it might be reſtored to its ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Purity. The <hi>Church of England</hi> with all its great <hi>Excellencies,</hi> and valuable <hi>Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,</hi> was thus Reformed; the Spiritual Powers being ruled and governed by the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2187:16"/> Secular in the Exerciſe of their Eccleſiaſtical Authority. And has the CHURCH yet a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right to take the Judicial Cognizance of Religion wholly out of the Hands of thoſe Men, by whom it has been preſerved from Deſtruction? What Reaſon or Neceſſity can there be for that? If by theſe Means the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the CHURCH ſhould once again fall into ill Hands, as it has done in former Times; it may in the unhappy Event be found ſetting up for Authority to <hi>corrupt</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, inſtead of <hi>preſerving</hi> it. And that too without leaving the Secular Potentates a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Authority to retrieve and reform it a ſecond time. And this alſo is a juſt Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Reaſonableneſs, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch a Claim.</p>
            <p>IV. SUCH an Exempt <hi>Independent Authority</hi> in the Church, ſeems wholly Inconſiſtent with that Intereſt and Care and Concern for Religion which Chriſtian Kings and Princes are alway ſuppoſed to have; and the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and Defence of which is one great End and Purpoſe of all their Authority. Till I ſee farther Reaſon againſt it than what has yet been ſhewn, I cannot but believe that the Civil Government in their Way, and by a due Exerciſe of their Power, is concerned
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2187:17"/> for the Good of Mens Souls, to promote Virtue and true Religion as well as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Paſtors of Chriſt's Flock. And if they are, then, to exclude their Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes and Matters, is to rob them of one great Part of their Sovereignty. It is in effect to confine all the Authority of Princes only to the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Peace, and Order, and Juſtice in Human Societies without any Regard to GOD and Religion. And I know of no good Reaſon that can be given for this. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' GOD the FATHER, for the Honour of our Bleſſed Redeemer, and the more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Accompliſhing our Redemption, has given him a Church and a Kingdom within his own Dominions, and allowed Him his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Miniſters and Governors of this CHURCH under his own Divine Authority: Yet I hope theſe Gentlemen will not ſay that this carries along with it a Devolution of all Power and Authority in religious Affairs from Princes to Biſhops, from the Governors of the State to thoſe of the Church. And if it does not, then the Secular Powers ought not in any ſuch Affairs to have their Authority and Juriſdiction excluded. That would be to ſubvert one of the main Ends of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, which was, That <hi>under them we might</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2187:17"/> 
               <hi>live peaceable and quiet Lives</hi> in <hi>Godlineſs</hi> as <note place="margin">1 Tim. ii. 2.</note> well as in common <hi>Honeſty.</hi> Theſe Gentlemen I know will allow Kings and Princes to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe all their Authority in the <hi>Defence</hi> of the Church, and for the <hi>Protection</hi> of its Powers, and the <hi>Support</hi> of it in the Execution of its Laws, altho' nothing to its Diſadvantage. And is it ſo then at laſt, that by virtue of Chriſt's Commiſſion, Kings and Princes have no more to do with Religious Matters, than only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Directions of the Church to miniſter to the <hi>Support</hi> of the Spiritual Juriſdiction, when ever they think ſit ſo to <hi>Modify</hi> their Power? I hope that all Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Kings will be ſenſible what Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Favours ſuch Churchmen intend them, in admitting them to ſo great a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege? And muſt they in all other Caſes be diſcharg'd of all Regard and Concern for GOD and RELIGION in the Government of their People? Sure I am, that it was not ſo under the Jewiſh Diſpenſation, when this Separation of the Prieſthood from the Secular Powers firſt began. Kings did then inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle in Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, and regulate the Affairs of Religion, and had Juriſdiction in the Government of the Church.</p>
            <p>The Ark of the Covenant which none might look into, or ſo much as touch it, but
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2187:18"/> the Prieſts alone: Was yet ſo far under the <note place="margin">2 Sam. vi.</note> Government and Authority of King <hi>David,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. xv.</note> that he commanded it to be removed firſt to this Place and then to that. He alſo diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted the ſeveral <hi>Courſes</hi> both of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. xxiii, xxiv.—xxiv.</note> 
               <hi>and Levites,</hi> and gave the <hi>Levites</hi> a new Law for their Offices, that they who before began not their Attendance till the <hi>Thirtieth</hi> Year of their Age ſhould now begin it <hi>at the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth.</hi> He took the Ark from the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle <note place="margin">2 Chron. i. 3, 5.</note> of the Congregation, and leaving that behind at <hi>Gibeon,</hi> he built a new Tent for it at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> How came he to meddle ſo much with that which was in the Peculiar Cuſtody of the Prieſts? The like was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <note place="margin">2 Chron. xxiv.—xxiii. 4.</note> done by <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> who alſo by his Royal Decree appointed the Paſſover to be kept, and called all the Ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to the Celebration of it, who had been hindred from it for a long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Solomon <hi>thruſt out</hi> Abiathar <hi>from being</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Kings ii. 27, 35.</note> 
               <hi>Prieſt unto the Lord.</hi> Which, let the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſay what they will to evade it, was as much a Deprivation as any one of thoſe they now complain of; and when he had done this, <hi>he put</hi> Zadock <hi>the Prieſt in the Room of</hi> Abiathar. The Altar of <hi>Bethel</hi> was deſtroy'd by King <hi>Joſiah;</hi> Idolatry was frequently pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and ſuppreſſed by their Kings, and the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2187:18"/> ſuffering Religion to be corrupted by intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Evil and Idolatrous Novelties into the Worſhip of GOD, is often charged as a Crime and a Blemiſh in the Adminiſtration of their Government. Now as the Inſtances menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in which they did exert their Power, were undeniable Acts of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Eccleſiaſtical Authority: So the Charge and Imputation of Guilt upon them in their Neglects of this kind, plainly ſhew that they had a juſt Authority and a rightful Juriſdiction therein. And if the Jewiſh Kings were allowed to have Power and Authority in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, and the Prieſthood claimed no Independent Power in Church Government, under that Diſpenſation in which the Adminiſtration of Divine Offices was as much ſeparated from the Secular Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates as it is now under the Goſpel: Some very good Reaſon, ſome ſtrong Proof, ſome very bright and clear Evidence ſhould be produced to convince one, that the Juriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which Kings exerciſed under one Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation is quite taken away by the other.</p>
            <p>ESPECIALLY too, when this claimed Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is not to be limitted to Articles of Faith, and Matters of Divine Revelation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but is extended to a Judicial Cognizance in all our <hi>moral Actions,</hi> as well as in thoſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2187:19"/> that are purely religious. And for the Kings and Potentates of the World not to ſubmit to the Sanctions and Determinations of ſuch Men in all Caſes of <hi>Morality;</hi> is arrogant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>Diſobedience</hi> to their <hi>ſpiritual Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vindic. Prop. 21.</note> and <hi>Rehellion</hi> againſt the <hi>Legates</hi> and <hi>Vicegerents of Chriſt.</hi> And to reſtrain eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Perſons in any extravagant Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this Kind, is repreſented by ſome Men as downright <hi>Perſecution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHAT an Original Piece of ſpiritual Pride is this? I would deſire any Reader ſeriouſly to conſider, that if ſuch Doctrines as theſe had been preached by the Apoſtles and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, Whether it would not have been the greateſt Diſadvantage imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to the Propagation of the Goſpel. And whether it would not have given all the Secular Potentates of the World a great and invincible Prejudice againſt it? What Heathen Emperor or King would have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced this Religion, or given any Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance at all to the Profeſſion of it, who ſhould have been told, That in the very Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute that this Religion was profeſſed by him, and became eſtabliſhed in his Dominions, he was to loſe one half of his Authority over his People? That he was no longer to have that Fullneſs of Juriſdiction and Power
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2187:19"/> which he had before, and which other Kings and Emperors enjoy'd round about him; but was now to give up his Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Supremacy in all <hi>Spiritual, Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Cauſes,</hi> and in all <hi>Moral Actions,</hi> into the Hands of his ſpiritual Governors of that Church, of which he was now becoming a Member? He is now no longer to claim an univerſal Supremacy in his Dominions, but himſelf becomes a <hi>Subject</hi> to his <hi>Subjects,</hi> and their <hi>ſpiritual Inferior;</hi> the Biſhops in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, being as ſo many <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual Monarchs,</hi> who have a Divine Right to tye up his Hands from having any thing to do in the Government of the Church, or in Matters of Religion? Would not all the Secular Potentates in the World have ſpurn'd at, and deſpiſed the Preachers of ſo ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a Religion, as an Impoſture and a Cheat, that under a Pretence of Godlineſs, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived to wreſt one great Part of their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority out of their Hands? And would not ſuch an Attempt as this too deſervedly have <hi>cauſed the Word of Truth to be evil ſpoken of?</hi> Moſt aſſuredly it would. And yet this is the very Thing that an Independent Authority in Church Government naturally, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally tends to.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2187:20"/>
            <p> DR. <hi>Hickes</hi> is pleaſed to ſay, <hi>Conſtit.</hi> p. 76. That the <hi>Governors of the Church loſe Nothing of their Power, Authority, or Juriſdiction by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Sovereign Princes into the Church.</hi> I beg leave to ask then, Whether it is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as reaſonable, both for the Honour and Intereſt of Chriſtianity, that Chriſtian Princes ſhould loſe Nothing of their <hi>Temporal Authority</hi> by embracing this our Holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? And if it be, I am ſure that the Schemes which are now laid out for Kings and Princes to rule by, under the Church's independent Power, cannot be of GOD; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they make Spoil and Havock of the ſecular Powers, and rob them of one en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Branch of their Sovereignty and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. And yet this is not the worſt Evil that attends this Claim. For,</p>
            <p>V. IT not only robs Kings of all Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty in religious and ſpiritual Affairs; but is extended alſo to their Adminiſtration of the Temporal. I have already obſerved, That theſe Gentlemen bring all the <hi>moral Actions</hi> of humane Life, under the peculiar Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of the ſpiritual Government of the CHURCH. Every Thing in which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of Men are concern'd, they claim, as falling wholly within this ſpiritual Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.
<pb facs="tcp:2187:20"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:2187:21"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:2187:21"/> ſo much as <hi>a Judge</hi> between two private <note place="margin">Luke xii. 14.</note> Men in the <hi>Diviſion</hi> of a ſmall Eſtate. But our Modern Independents in Church Government, make themſelves Judges of Kings, and of their Titles to their Thrones. They, in effect, divide the Kingdoms of the Earth according to their Deciſions and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations. By a pretended Supremacy from CHRIST, they put a Check upon the Legiſlature in the Laws that they provide for the Security of the Nation, and labour to controul the States of the Realm in the Adminiſtration of their ſecular Affairs. They ſanctify even Sedition and Rebellion by their <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Authority, and take upon them to abſolve the Subjects from all the ſtricteſt Oaths whereby they have ſworn Allegiance to their King, They endeavour to bind it upon the Conſciences of Men, to ſet up one King, and to dethrone another, according to their perſonal Sentiments and Opinions. Now I would willingly be informed by them what Part of CHRIST'S Commiſſion it is that gives them this Authority; or that in any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable Titles to the Throne makes them the Judges of it? And yet the Modern Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in Church Goverment, do not only aſſume all this to themſelves; but they alſo lay as much Streſs on their own Notions and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2187:22"/> Aſſertions of this Kind, as tho' they had a Spirit of Infallibility, or an immediate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation from Heaven. What leſs than this, could induce them to charge all the Great Men of our Church, however learned, and equally pious with themſelves, as Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Acting, and Praying, contrary to the eſſential Righteouſneſs of GOD, only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they teach, and act, and pray, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their particular Sentiments and Schemes in Civil Government? What is this, but to arrogate to themſelves a Spirit of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility in the Interpretation of thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on which they build their Notions and Opinions? Will not the Reader ſtand ſtill here and Pauſe a little, and Queſtion the Truth of what I ſay? Will he not think it incredible that ſpiritual Men ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach ſo near to Blaſphemy, as to ſet up their own political Principles, as the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Teſts of Truth and Righteouſneſs? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that CHRIST'S Commiſſion is of another Nature, and never was intended to authorize the Governors of the Church to frame the Government of Nations too ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their diſputable Models and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted Schemes; and to damn all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind as Hereticks, and Schiſmaticks, and Rebels, who will not come in to them, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2187:22"/> deſert the legal Conſtitutions of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. This is foreign to the Buſineſs of the Goſpel; the Propagation of the Chriſtian Faith, by Preaching, and Baptizing, and Adminiſtring Sacraments, and Training up Chriſtians in Holineſs and Devotion, is a Sphere at ſo great a Diſtance from all this of Secular Government and Political Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, that GOD certainly never gave the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors of the Church any Divine Authority therein. And therefore an <hi>Independent</hi> Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Church Governors, which is induſtriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet up to this End; muſt be an Impoſture and a Cheat, and contrary to the Will of CHRIST and of GOD. And Biſhops and Clergymen by Virtue of CHRIST'S Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may as well claim a Right to go into <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> and turn out the Judges, as giving Judgment <hi>contrary to the eſſential Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God;</hi> as to teach the People, that it is a Sin to be ſubject to the Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Kingdom where they live. This brings me to my</p>
            <p>VI. LAST Argument, which is, That this Independent Authority in the Government of the CHURCH., is utterly inconſiſtent with the <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Sovereignty</hi> of all Secular Potentates. Two ſuch Independent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2187:23"/> in the Government of the ſame Body of Men, appear utterly incompatible. They ſo frequently interfere, and thereby bring ſuch Miſchiefs and Diſtractions into the World, that they cannot poſſibly be both of them from GOD. He, who is a God of Peace and Order, and not of Confuſion, muſt not be ſuppoſed to have intended any two ſuch Powers without a Subordination of the one to the other.</p>
            <p>THE Supporters of that Claim, being aware of this Argument, would evade it by ſaying, That the Miſchiefs complained of, proceed not from the Inconſiſtency of two ſuch Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but from the Encroachments of the two contending Parties. And that all this would be prevented effectually, if each would keep within their proper Limits, and neither of 'em <hi>put their Sickle into the other's Harveſt.</hi> This is <note place="margin">Regale &amp; Pontiff. <hi>p.</hi> 15.</note> ſmoothly and finely ſaid indeed, but Nothing to the Purpoſe; becauſe it is Arguing againſt plain Matter of Fact. For they both of them <hi>claim a Right to the ſame Harveſt;</hi> and who then ſhall judge between them to preſerve the Peace and Quiet of the Chriſtian World? Are not all our preſent Contentions and Feuds about the uncontroulable <hi>Supremacy</hi> of the Governors of the Church in all Religious and Spiritual Cauſes? And is it not apparent
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2187:23"/> undeniably, that the very End of Claiming ſuch a Power, is, to protect ſome Men from the Authority of the STATE? How then is it poſſible that two ſuch Contending ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Sovereigns ſhould exerciſe their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Powers, one to remove, and the other to ſupport thoſe Men; and yet the Subjects be bound to obey them both? How can two ſuch Supremacies ſubſiſt in the ſame Body of Men, when almoſt every Act of the one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences the other? When in ſome Caſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every Exerciſe of Spiritual Authority, one Way or other influences, and either weakens or controuls the Temporal? A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Defender of this Spiritual, Eccleſiaſtical Independency, ſaw the Neceſſity of grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That CHRIST <hi>gave the Church no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Regal. &amp; Pontif. <hi>p.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>that could poſſibly interfere with the Civil Powers.</hi> This Aſſertion I own to be very true; and therefore if the <hi>Non-jurors</hi> will but grant me that, which I think no reaſonable Man can deny, <hi>viz.</hi> That GOD has given to <hi>Secular</hi> Powers as full an Authority for the Support and Security of the STATE, as He has to the <hi>Spiritual</hi> for the Defence of the CHURCH; and conſequently, that every Act of <hi>Independent Power</hi> of the Church, that <hi>interferes with the Civil Powers,</hi> is contrary to the Will of GOD, and to the Intention of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2187:24"/> CHRIST'S Commiſſion: I readily join Iſſue with them upon this Cauſe, and am very willing to try the Force of this Principle in thoſe particular Caſes that are made the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of our preſent Diſputes. And they are, 1. The Election. 2. The Deprivation of Biſhops and Clergymen.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the Election of Biſhops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gymen, it is granted, That as the CHURCH has the ſole Authority of <hi>Ordaining</hi> them, ſo with that they have of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> a common natural Right to take Care of the <hi>Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the Perſons to be ordained, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in Divine Service. But then, it is indeed reaſonable, that the CHURCH in the Exerciſe of this Power, ſhould not claim a Divine Authority to thruſt and force upon a Chriſtian State ſuch Biſhops and Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as are avowed Enemies to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and National Conſtitution where they live. For this is actually to <hi>interfere with the Civil Powers.</hi> It's highly reaſonable that Kings and Princes ſhould be well-aſſured of the Fidelity and Allegiance of their Clergy; ſeeing that They and their Government, have an Intereſt therein; and both the Peace and Safety of their Secular Affairs may be very much influenced by their good or evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2187:24"/> If therefore on this Account the Laws of the Land give to our Kings the Nomination of the Perſons that are to be made Biſhops; it is indiſputably <hi>interfering with the Civil Powers,</hi> to ſay that they have no Right there to; and that every ſuch Nomination is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of the CHURCH'S Power. If the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of that Power be at all to be judged of by its Conſiſtency with the Peace and Safety of the STATE, it is then as clear as any Demonſtration in the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> that CHRIST'S Commiſſion has given no ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Power in the Choice of Biſhops; becauſe that actually breaks in upon the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Power of Kings and Princes, even in the Adminiſtration of their National Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For let us reflect, Is it not by Virtue of this pretended <hi>Divine Right,</hi> and <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Juriſdiction, that we ſee ſuch vile and ſcandalous Practices in our Days, as the Primitive Chriſtians were wholly Strangers to; and would have Proteſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt with the utmoſt Abhorrence and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation? By Virtue of this pretended Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Authority, the <hi>Non-jurors</hi> take upon them to <hi>conſecrate</hi> Biſhops, and <hi>ordain</hi> Prieſts, not only in Oppoſition to the STATE, but with a direct Intention, if it be poſſible, to overturn it. For the firſt Thing that ſuch
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2187:25"/> Biſhops and Clergymen have to do, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all Allegiance to the KING upon the Throne, and all Regard to the Preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Kingdom. To treat the KING as an <hi>Uſurper,</hi> to teach a <hi>Nullity</hi> in all the Oaths that are taken to Him, tho' by moſt ſolemn Sanctions of the Law. To ſet up an Eccleſiaſtical Community, and gather Congregations againſt Him, and therein to pray for another pretended King, whom the Nation has ſolemnly abjured, and proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Traitor. Will not all this be called <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfering with the Civil Powers?</hi> If it be; I think then, it muſt be granted, that all this is directly contrary to CHRIST'S Commiſſion, and to the whole Deſign of it? If there be a Diſpute about the Title to the Crown, moſt certainly the States of the Realm are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Judges and Determiners of the Matter: And CHRIST by his Commiſſion, has given the Biſhops and Paſtors of his CHURCH no Divine Authority or Juriſdiction in ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations. If therefore the Governors of the Church, inſtead of taking Care, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Truſt, that the Biſhops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of the CHURCH, be Men of ſober Lives, and ſound Religion, will go ſo much farther as to claim a Divine Right in the Choice of all the Biſhops excluſive of the Nomination of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2187:25"/> the Prince, only to embarraſs his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and embroil his Affairs: It is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that ſuch a Spiritual Power cannot be of GOD, as it is that all Secular <hi>Powers are of</hi> GOD. Becauſe two ſuch Independent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities in or over the ſame Body of Men, cannot poſſibly conſiſt together. The one will inevitably <hi>interfere</hi> with, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of the other; and ſuch inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Oppoſition, Confuſion and Diſtraction in humane Society, could never be deſigned or intended by Almighty GOD. The like may be ſaid</p>
            <p n="2">2. AS to the Deprivation of Biſhops and Clergymen.</p>
            <p>I COULD heartily wiſh, there had been no Occaſion for the unhappy Debate that I am now upon. And what I ſhall ſay upon it, I intend with all Deference to the unhappy Perſons who were deprived. But ſeeing a pretended <hi>Invalidity</hi> in their Deprivation is made the Occaſion of a <hi>Schiſm</hi> from our CHURCH, and of great Confuſions in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Doubtleſs, common Juſtice ought to be done to the lawful Secular Powers we live under.</p>
            <p>NOW, if it be indeed true, that CHRIST <hi>has given no Power to his Church that interferes</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:2187:26"/> 
               <hi>with the Civil Powers;</hi> and moſt true it is, and neceſſary for the due Government of the World that it ſhould be ſo; the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of it is, That CHRIST by His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion has given no ſuch Authority to His CHURCH, as to keep Biſhops and Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in their reſpective Sees, when the STATE finds it neceſſary for the Safety of a Nation to turn them out. For this alſo is to ſet up Powers that are incompatible; both whoſe Commands cannot be obey'd, becauſe they command contrary and inconſiſtent Things.</p>
            <p>THIS was the Caſe of thoſe unhappy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Clergy, who were deprived for not giving the uſual Oaths of Fidelity to the Civil Government of King <hi>William.</hi> Their Principles and Practices, as to that Government, were ſuch, that it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come impoſſible for them to execute their Spiritual Offices in the CHURCH, with any Security to the Peace and Safety of the STATE. They could not perform Divine-Service in Publick, becauſe they would not own the Authority of the King, who was to be prayed for therein; The Biſhops could not ordain other Clergymen, for the ſame Reaſon; They could not do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out obliging them, by the Laws of the Land,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2187:26"/> to own thoſe Secular Powers, whom they themſelves did not own. They could not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the Clergy, as Biſhops by the Laws of the Land are bound to govern them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Teaching them, and Inſtructing them to teach their People the Duty of Obedience to that King, whom they themſelves looked on as an unlawful King. Neither could they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Ends, or do the Buſineſs of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by ſitting in Parliament, as the Law expects and requires, that all the Biſhops of the Kingdom ſhould do. Nay, in all their Exerciſe of Divine Offices, they muſt undeniably lie under a ſtrong Byaſs and Temptation of inſtilling dangerous Doctrines, and Principles inconſiſtent with the Peace and Security of the Kingdom. Can it be ſuppoſed then, that any National Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wants a ſufficient and <hi>competent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of removing ſuch Biſhops from their Sees, and of putting other Orthodox Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in their Room? And muſt They ask the Clergy's Leave to do this? Or muſt they borrow <hi>a competent Authority</hi> from the CHURCH to do this effectually? Miſerable are the Princes who are in ſuch a Caſe! Wretched is the Kingdom that wants <hi>a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Authority</hi> to do any Thing which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears neceſſary to be done with any of its
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2187:27"/> Subjects, of what Order ſoever, to ſupport it ſelf, and preſerve its own Authority. Who then can believe that Almighty GOD ever intended this? Thoſe who object againſt the <hi>Validity</hi> of ſuch a Deprivation, ſhould conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der two Things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. THAT there is no Perſecution of Chriſtianity in it. Had thoſe Biſhops been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived for any Doctrines or Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, it would have looked more plauſibly on their Side, and might with more Reaſon have been called Perſecution. Or, if upon their Deprivation, their Diſtricts and Sees had been left deſtitute of Orthodox Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops regularly conſecrated to perform the Divine Offices, as others had done before them: This would have made a great Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Caſe. But when it is for an avowed Diſaffection to the eſtabliſhed Civil Government, and judged neceſſary for the Security of it; that <hi>Neceſſity</hi> proves it lawful, and anſwers all Objections that can poſſibly be brought againſt it. And therefore, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that ſuch a Deprivation is not <hi>valid,</hi> as to the People living within their Diſtricts of ſuch deprived Biſhops, becauſe it is not <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical;</hi> is in effect ſaying nothing at all. For Deprivation ſignifies nothing to the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2187:27"/> Purpoſe, if it does not in the Effects of it, bind all the Conſciences of the Subjects to diſown the Authority of the Perſons ſo deprived; and diſcharge them from all Obligations of future Submiſſion to, and Communion with them. This is a Power without which Civil Government cannot ſtand: and therefore Secular Powers muſt be granted to have a <hi>competent Authority</hi> to all ſuch Purpoſes; or elſe they are not only <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Inferiors,</hi> but even <hi>Slaves</hi> to their <hi>ſpiritual Sovereigns,</hi> and muſt depend preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly on the Good-will and Favour of their Clergy, whether they ſhall ſit eaſy and ſafe on their Thrones, or no. And all the Laws, and Canons, and Conſtitutions of the CHURCH, if they be wiſe, and good, and chriſtian, muſt be made with a due Regard and Subſerviency to this End, or elſe they loſe all <hi>their Validity,</hi> and are to be looked upon as Nothing. For this is a ſure Principle never to be diſputed, That all National Governments have as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and <hi>competent</hi> an <hi>Authority</hi> to do every Thing which is neceſſary to preſerve the STATE, as the Biſhops and Clergy can have for the Support of RELIGION and the CHURCH.</p>
            <p>AND if this Authority will extend to the <hi>valid</hi> Deprivation of the diſaffected, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2187:28"/> Governors of the Church, the plain Conſequence of it is, That all the Subjects of the Kingdom are in Duty and Conſcience diſcharged from any farther ſpiritual Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to, or Communion with the Perſons ſo deprived. What is it then that our <hi>Non-jurors</hi> mean by Exclaiming againſt this, even as tho' it were a Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt? To tell the World, That all other Biſhops, who will not adhere to the deprived ones, <hi>can perform no valid Acts of Prieſthood; their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Hickes.</hi> Collect. <hi>p</hi> 32.</note> 
               <hi>are Sin, and their Sacraments, no Sacraments, and their Abſolution, Null, and of no Force.</hi> That all other Chriſtians, who are not in the Communion of the deprived Biſhops, <hi>are cut off from the Church of Chriſt, can have no Benefit by His Promiſes, no Aſſiſtance of His Grace, no Mercy thro' His Blood. Nay, that altho' they die Martyrs for Chriſt, yet Martyrdom it ſelf cannot make amends for this Sin.</hi> If a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to our Goſpel were to hear this, he would certainly conclude, that Chriſtianity aimed at Nothing more than the Exaltation of the CHURCH'S Power; and that Nothing greater was required to Salvation, than to own theſe deprived Biſhops to be the Heads of it. Whereas, in Truth, the Commiſſion given, is only to preach the Goſpel, to adminiſter the Sacraments, and to exerciſe ſuch Offices,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2187:28"/> and ſuch Powers, as ſhall be neceſſary to the Propagation of the Chriſtian Religion: Without any Check upon Secular Potentates in their Adminiſtration of Civil Government, or any Exemption from their Juriſdiction. They <hi>have no Authority that interferes with Civil Powers.</hi> To confirm all which, it muſt not be forgotten,</p>
            <p n="2">2. THAT in this Deprivation the STATE took away no Power which the CHURCH truly and properly ſpeaking gives. Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi> indeed, inſinuates, <hi>p.</hi> 24. That <hi>as only Biſhops have from Chriſt a Right to ordain; ſo they only have a Right to deprive one another.</hi> But this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is formed with more Cunning than Ingenuity, and the Oppoſition is not fairly put. It ſhould not have been between <hi>Ordain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Depriving;</hi> but <hi>Ordaining</hi> and <hi>Depoſing</hi> from the Sacred Order of the Prieſthood. In the one the CHURCH gives, in the other She takes away Her ſpiritual Authority. But <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving</hi> is of another Nature; it leaves the Perſons all the Catholick Authority which the CHURCH gave, if they can find Places where they may lawfully Exerciſe it; and only reſtrains them from doing ſo in ſuch and ſuch Dominions. It is chiefly Remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them from the Diſtricts and Sees which they held of the Secular Powers, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2187:29"/> from all Right to the Exerciſe of their Spiritual Offices among any of the King's Subjects. And if Kings and Princes have not a <hi>competent Authority</hi> to do this, they are too weak to ſtand, and conſequently, much weaker than GOD and CHRIST ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that Civil Government ſhould be.</p>
            <p>THE chief Objections to what is here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, are theſe three.</p>
            <p n="1">I. IT is pleaded, <hi>That there is ſuch a Divine Relation between a Biſhop and the People of his Diſtrict, as no Secular Powers can take away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. THAT <hi>the Authority in ſpiritual Affairs, here allowed to Kings and Princes, is contrary to the Practice and</hi> Principles <hi>of the firſt three Hundred Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. THAT <hi>this is bringing the Church and its Clergy into Slavery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I. As to the <hi>Divine Relation</hi> pretended to be between a Biſhop and the People of his See or Diſtrict: Pray, how comes that about? It is compared, I know, by ſome <note place="margin">Reg. &amp; Pont. <hi>p.</hi> 3.</note> Men to <hi>Marriage.</hi> But who made that Match, or gave the divine Sanction to the Contract? Or if that were true, how comes
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2187:29"/> there to be ſo many common Cauſes of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce? In ſhort, this is the Notion of thoſe only, who make every Thing that has been occaſionally done by the Governors of the Church, to have been done by a divine and unchangeable Authority. But the only Way to judge rightly of this Matter, is, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what is the <hi>original Ground</hi> of that Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by whoſe Deſignation and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity it has been made. Now as to this,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I BELIEVE, that every Body will grant, That in promoting Biſhops to ſuch and ſuch Sees, and Clergymen to their Diſtricts or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, a Regard ought, and will be had, to the Sentiments and the Judgment of the Spiritual Governors of the Church; who, as I ſaid above, in Conſequence of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from CHRIST to plant and govern it, muſt be ſuppoſed Inveſted with a <hi>Truſt</hi> as to the ſpiritual Qualifications of the Perſons to be employed in Holy Offices. And this Care, and Truſt, and juſt Authority, they are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to diſcharge in their Admiſſion of Perſons into Holy Orders. In which they have Authority to provide, that no Perſons unqualified, ſhould be admitted into the Service of GOD. But then, when the Church has effectually taken this Care, it muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be granted alſo in the</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2187:30"/> 2. <hi>Second Place,</hi> THAT Chriſtian Princes and States have both an <hi>Intereſt</hi> in this Affair, and a <hi>Truſt</hi> alſo committed to <hi>Them</hi> in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding proper Spiritual Guides and Paſtors for their People. And where they have both an <hi>Intereſt</hi> and a <hi>Truſt,</hi> it will be very hard to ſay, that they have no Authority. Suppoſe that the Governors of the CHURCH ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to appoint ſuch Perſons as the STATE can have no Confidence in, or no Security from, muſt they be allowed no Authority, even where their Peace and Safety appear to be very deeply concern'd? Sure this is too unreaſonable and abſurd to be believed. Or, again, Suppoſe that the Governors of the CHURCH ſhould be careleſs, and neglect pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for their Sees, would not the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Powers be bound to ſupply that Defect, and to take Gare that the People ſhould not want proper Guides and Paſtors? It is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd then to think, that they have no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in a Matter which they are bound in Conſcience to take Care of. Now as all this ſeems very agreeable to common Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; let us go on, and conſider</p>
            <p n="3">3. WHAT has been the Practice of the CHURCH in this Particular. And here we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2187:30"/> ſhall find, that generally ſpeaking, every One who appeared to have an Intereſt in the Management of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs were allowed to have an Influence, and ſome Power in the Deſignation of the Perſon to be employed in ſuch a Place or Diſtrict.</p>
            <p>THE CHURCH commits a Catholick Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or Authority in Conſecration or Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which Authority is to be exerciſed ſo far as lawfully it may, thro' the whole CHURCH of CHRIST, without any Aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this or that particular Juriſdiction. So the Form of Conſecration runs with us: <hi>Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt for the Office and Work of a Biſhop in the Church of</hi> GOD. And that ſuch was the Manner of Primitive Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Reverend and very Learned Dr. <hi>Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ch. Gov. <hi>p.</hi> 452.</note> now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> proves from hence, That Miniſters were then ſometimes ordained without any Deſignation at all to particular Diſtricts. And indeed, without this general Commiſſion in Ordination, I do not ſee how they could be ſaid to be inveſted with a Spiritual Power or Authority thro' the Whole <hi>Chriſtian Church.</hi> This Power then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus convey'd by the <hi>Church;</hi> the Deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Perſons to this or that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Diſtrict, was made ſeveral Ways. In the Apoſtles Time, ſuch and ſuch Perſons were
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2187:31"/> ſent by them to ſuch and ſuch Cities, and great Towns, to miniſter therein, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the CHURCH according to the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons given. But afterwards the Clergy of the vacant Dioceſe ſometimes choſe their own Biſhop, and ſometimes the eldeſt Presbyter ſucceeded in Courſe. But then, to ſhew that every Thing which the Biſhops and Clergy at that Time did, was not done by a <hi>Divine</hi> Authority: What was ſometimes done in this Affair by the Clergy, was ſometimes done by the People alſo, when the Biſhops of another Province advanced any new Biſhop to a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant See, it was always done with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Approbation of the People. Uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Approbation and Conſent of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was had, as to the Perſon, before his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration. The forementioned Right Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhop has cited a Paſſage out of the VIII<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Book of the <hi>Apoſtolical Conſtitutions,</hi> c. 4. in which it is decreed, That <hi>ſuch a Biſhop muſt be ordained as was elected by the People for his emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Merit, and their Conſent was to be a third Time asked.</hi> And to the ſame Purpoſe there are ſeveral Paſſages in St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> whereby it plainly appears, that the People had ſo much Authority, that they were uſually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, and their Vote and Conſent asked in the Deſignation of the Biſhop that was to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2187:31"/> preſide over them. Which ſhews moſt plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſuch a Deſignation was not made by the <hi>divine appropriated Powers</hi> of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Clergy only. And it is very well known, that what the People had at the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, came by Degrees into the Hands of Kings and Princes. They had the Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Biſhops to their ſeveral Sees; and I would therefore have a very good Reaſon given, why thoſe Rulers who had Authority in Promoting them, ſhould not be allowed the ſame in Removing them. Or how ſuch a Removal can be called an <hi>Invaſion of the ſacred Rights of the Prieſthood;</hi> when they were promoted by the Election or Nomination of the Laity, as well as of the Biſhops?</p>
            <p>I KNOW it will be ſaid, That all this was only a prudent Condeſcention and Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the People of their Flock, without any Authority. But to this I anſwer, Does not Voting, and Electing, and an almoſt conſtant and eſtabliſh'd Uſage of Conſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſons to ſuch and ſuch Diſtricts by Voting and Electing, look like a good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Authority in the Matter? And would the Fathers of the Church have ſuffered all this, if they had had the ſame Notions with ſome in our Days? Would they have conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended ſo far, if they had known it to be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2187:32"/> an <hi>Invaſion</hi> of the CHURCH'S <hi>Independent Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers?</hi> No certainly; their Practice in this Caſe, is a ſufficient Demonſtration that they had no ſuch Sentiments.</p>
            <p>AND indeed, how ſhall we judge, or how ſhall we know what are the CHURCH'S pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Rights, and what not; but by the Words of CHRIST'S Commiſſion, and the Practice of the moſt Primitive Churches thereupon? The Performance of thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Offices which CHRIST by His Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion has taken away from the Civil Powers, and veſted in a diſtinct Order of Men, we own to be the peculiar Authorities of the CHURCH. And accordingly, the Primitive Fathers did not allow the Laity to have Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority therein. They never condeſcended ſo far as to ſuffer them either to conſecrate the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> or to lay on Hands in Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. When therefore as to the Deſignation of Biſhops to ſuch and ſuch particular Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricts, CHRIST'S Commiſſion gives no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining or Appropriating Rules at all, and the conſtant Practice of the CHURCH has been to admit the Laity to have an <hi>Intereſt</hi> and a <hi>Vote</hi> therein, and to promote by their <hi>Election:</hi> I do not know what can confute the Claim of a <hi>Divine Relation,</hi> and an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Authority</hi> herein, if this will not.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:2187:32"/>
            <p> IF then the Deſignation of Biſhops and Clergymen to their ſeveral Diſtricts be no Part of the CHURCH'S <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>unalienable Rights;</hi> certainly the Removal or Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch Perſons, can be no <hi>Invaſion</hi> of them; becauſe doubtleſs they who have a <hi>competent Authority</hi> to promote, muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to have the ſame alſo to Remove.</p>
            <p>THE Concluſion of the Whole then, is, There is no ſuch Thing in our Days as a Clergyman's having a Divine Right to his Diſtrict. His Claim and Right is wholly Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and Legal; founded on the Laws of the Land, and the eſtabliſhed Conſtitutions of the CHURCH and Country in which we live. Conſequently then, what the STATE does in a legal Way in ſuch Deprivations, is done by a <hi>competent Authority;</hi> it is <hi>Valid</hi> in all Reſpects; and binds the Conſciences of all Men. It transfers the Obligations, as to Religious Communion, from the former Poſſeſſor to the latter. It makes it our Duty to adhere to ſuch Biſhops, as in ſuch Caſes, the Laws of the Land regularly advance: And it makes our adhering to the Communion of the Biſhops ſo deprived, to be both ſinful and ſchiſmatical.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:2187:33"/>
            <p> II. THE ſecond Objection is, That what I have here advanced, ſeems not to agree with the <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> of the CHURCH for the firſt three hundred Years.</p>
            <p>As to the Practice of the CHURCH in thoſe Times, I have in ſome Meaſure thus accounted for it already. That it proceeded from the Exigencies and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of Affairs at the Time when the Chriſtians were either under Perſecution, and ſo were conſtrained to act in Oppoſition to their Secular Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, becauſe Chriſtianity could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be propagated: Or elſe, it was done under the Connivance and Permiſſion of ſuch Temporal Powers. In either of which Caſes, what was <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be done by the Biſhops and Governors of the CHURCH for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of the Chriſtian Religion, they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly had a Divine Right and Authority from GOD to do. But then, in ſuch Caſes, the CHURCH did not claim a Divine Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Excluding the Juriſdiction of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors and Secular Governors; but they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded themſelves, by refuſing to intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in this Government. Even the mildeſt of the Heathen Emperors, who, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us, <hi>Apol.</hi> cap. v. forbid the Chriſtians to be enquired after, or perſecuted, ſeem to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2187:33"/> have dealt with them, only as <hi>Gallio</hi> the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty of <hi>Achaia</hi> did, <hi>I will be no Judge of ſuch</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts xviii 15.</note> 
               <hi>Matters.</hi> When therefore the Chriſtian Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Clergy were ſo far either neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or favoured by their Heathen Governors as to be left to themſelves; they had Nothing more to do than to make wiſe Laws, and proper Canons, and ſee them duly executed. And if againſt thoſe, who among themſelves were mutinous, and turbulent, and ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, they pleaded the juſt Obligation of their Sanctions, and ſet forth very emphatically the Diſorder and Guilt of thoſe who in ſuch Caſes revolted from their proper Biſhop, and deſpiſed his Authority, and ſeparated from his Communion; they certainly Argued very juſtly, and Acted very rightly. All Chriſtians were bound in Conſcience to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves to ſuch good and wiſe Rules, and to ſubmit to ſuch juſt and lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. But what is all this, to the Rights of the Temporal Powers, whoſe Authority does not appear ſo much as once to have fallen under their Debates for the firſt three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years.</p>
            <p>WHEN the <hi>Romans</hi> had conquered <hi>Judea,</hi> they yet left the <hi>Jews</hi> in a great Meaſure to the Management of their own Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. And what <hi>Herod,</hi> or the high
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2187:34"/> Prieſt and the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> in ſuch Caſes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted or ordained, was doubtleſs in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be obeyed; and it was a Sin to be mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous and ſeditious againſt them. But ſure this Privilege could never be extended to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Power and Authority of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperors. So here, the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors put the Chriſtians under a Neceſſity of Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing independently on the Temporal Power, becauſe they would not concern themſelves therein. But this does not at all prove, that therefore all Secular Powers muſt for ever be excluded. I am amazed therefore, to find ſuch a Fondneſs, as I do, for the <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Sentiments</hi> of the <hi>Cyprianick Age</hi> in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy; I cannot but ſmile at Mens At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to determine it by the Practice and Principles of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> or any other Father of thoſe Times. All that they ſay, is out of the Queſtion, and foreign to the Purpoſe. They only plead the Power and Authority of the <hi>Church's</hi> Sanctions among themſelves; and the Guilt of ſeparating from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of their Biſhops, while there was no other who would meddle in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it. In ſuch Caſes, theirs was the only proper Authority to be regarded; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Secular Powers had declined all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction therein. But this is no more a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2187:34"/> Proof that the Authority of Kings and Princes muſt for ever be excluded from all Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Affairs, than the Decrees of <hi>Herod,</hi> and the Jewiſh <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> are a Proof that <hi>Julius,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> had no Authority in <hi>Judaea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHAT ſhall we ſay then to Dr. <hi>Hickes,</hi> who would ſend all Chriſtian Emperors and Kings to theſe very Times to learn new Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and to know from theſe Examples <hi>what Power they ought to exerciſe in Eccleſiaſtical</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prop. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Affairs?</hi> Certainly this is a very odd Way of Arguing, That becauſe Heathen Emperors <hi>would not</hi> meddle with the Government of the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> therefore Chriſtian Kings and Princes <hi>muſt not.</hi> As tho' the Neglects and Diſregards of the one, were to be a Bar and an Interdict to the juſt Rights and Claims of the other. That this is the Truth of the Caſe, and that there is no more than this in it, will be undeniably plain and clear,</p>
            <p>3. FROM the great Conceſſions and large Compliances that the Chriſtian Biſhops and Clergy ſoon made when the <hi>Roman</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors favoured their Intereſt, and interpoſed their Authority in the Management and Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of the Affairs of the CHURCH. If the Primitive Fathers had had the ſame Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents with Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi> and his Friends, as to the CHURCH'S <hi>Divine Right</hi> to an <hi>Independent</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:2187:35"/> 
               <hi>Authority;</hi> it is impoſſible that they ſhould have given in to the Authority and Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Emperors, as they are found to have done. And whether they will impute it to the Ignorance of the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or whether they will make them the firſt Betrayers of the CHURCH'S ſacred Rights, I leave to themſelves; let them account for it as they pleaſe. I am contented to obſerve, from a very learned Treatiſe of our preſent <note place="margin">Author. Chriſtian Prin. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. c. 17, 21, 27, 34, 35.</note> great and good Archbiſhop, who has ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Aſſertions with Authorities which are indiſputable, That no ſooner did the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Euſeb. Vit Conſt.</hi> Lib. III. c. 6, 7, 10, 12, 13, 17. <hi>Contanſtine</hi> called the firſt general Council by his Imperial Authority, appointed the City <hi>Nice</hi> in <hi>Bithynia</hi> for the Place of their Meeting, and on the Day ſet for opening the Synod he came and ſat among them, and Reaſoned with them and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their Differences.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> Lib. IV. c. 42, 43. He ſummoned another Council to meet at <hi>Tyre.</hi> A. D. 335; and Threatned thoſe who diſobey'd his Summons with Baniſhment, or Ejectment out of his See; afterward he adjourned it to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> To this Council <hi>Athanaſius</hi> came in pure Obedience to the Emperor, and appealed from it to his Authority.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ib.</hi> Lib. I. c. 44. <hi>Euſebius</hi> commends <hi>Conſtantine</hi> for his Piety and Religious Care in all this.</p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Cave. Hiſt.</hi> Lit. Vol. 2. p. 152. In the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> at <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage.</hi> A. D. 411. <hi>Marcellinus</hi> the Emperors Commiſſioner di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the <hi>Manner</hi> of their Proceeding, appointing Seven Biſhops only of a Side to enter into Debate; and in the end gave Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in favour of the <hi>Orthodox.</hi> And when upon <hi>Marcellinus</hi> his Death the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> would have had all that had been done re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinded; <hi>Honorius</hi> confirmed their Decrees and made them <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ib. p.</hi> 158, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon the Feuds, and contrary Decrees in the Council of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> A. D. 431. between <hi>John Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> againſt <hi>Neſtorius, Theodoſius</hi> the Emperor commands all that had been done on both Sides to be <hi>reſcinded;</hi> and upon a full and true Information of what had paſt, he <hi>confirm'd</hi> the Decrees made againſt <hi>Neſtorius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to Imperial Laws in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs I will mention a Few only out of the <hi>Code</hi> and <hi>Novells</hi> of <hi>Juſtinian. God.</hi> Lib. I. <hi>Tit.</hi> iii. cap. 8. If a Clergyman gave falſe Witneſs in a Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niary Caſe, he was to be <hi>ſuſpended from his Office for Three Years;</hi> if in a <hi>Criminal Cauſe,</hi> to be <hi>Degraded</hi> from the Prieſtly Office, <hi>clericatûs honore nudatus, &amp;c. ib.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Novel. Coll.</hi> ix. <hi>Tit.</hi> vi. 123. cap. x. A Clergyman playing at Tables, or ſtanding by to lay Wagers, or look on, was to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended for three Years; <hi>jubemus tribus annis, a venerabili Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterio prohiberi.</hi> ib. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</p>
                  <p>He that ſhall give or take Money to procure the Election or Ordination of a Miniſter, was to be <hi>degraded; a gradu Sacerdotij retrahatur.</hi> ib. <hi>c.</hi> 31.</p>
                  <p>A Biſhop not Conſecrated according to ſome particular Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Conſtitutions was to be depoſed. <hi>Jubemus hunc omnibus modis Epicſopatu depelli, Novel.</hi> ix. <hi>Tit.</hi> vi. 123, 1.</p>
                  <p>A Presbyter ordained before examination, if he had been accuſed as unfit, was to be depoſed, <hi>a Sacerdotio repellatur</hi> c. 2.</p>
                  <p>A Biſhop deſerting his See and not returning in a ſet Time was to be <hi>Deprived. Ab Epiſcopatu expelli.</hi> ib. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>If a Biſhop or Presbyter excommunicates any without hearing his Cauſe, the Perſon unjuſtly excommunicated ſhall be Abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by another Presbyter, and he that unjuſtly excommunicated him, ſhall <hi>himſelf be excommunicated.</hi> ib. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p>If a Biſhop that was deprived, or depoſed, <hi>Sacerdotio pulſus,</hi> preſumed to return to the City he had belonged to, he was to be confined in a Monaſtry. <hi>ib.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Biſhop permitting a Deacon to Marry after he was ordained was to be <hi>deprived; expellatur ab Epiſcopatu,</hi> and a Presbyter ſo Marrying was to be degraded; <hi>expellatur a clero.</hi> ib. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p>Many more Laws of this kind equivalent to our Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, might be mentioned; and they all demonſtrate that the Chriſtians of thoſe Ages knew no ſuch Principle, as the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Power of the Church in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs.</p>
               </note> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperors concern themſelves in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Church and the Government of it, but the Biſhops admitted them to ſummon
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2187:35"/> Councils by their <hi>Imperial Authority;</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> of their Meeting; to direct the <hi>Matter</hi> to be treated on, and the <hi>Manner</hi> of their Proceeding. To <hi>Preſide</hi> in, and <hi>Regulate</hi> their Debates; to exerciſe <hi>Authority</hi> over their Declarations and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, ſometimes to <hi>Revoke,</hi> and ſometimes to <hi>Suſpend</hi> their Decrees. Sometimes they
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2187:36"/> not only made Laws about Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, without the Clergy; but even regulated their Qualifications, and puniſhed their Miſcarriages; ſometimes with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to the Church to Degrade them, and ſometimes to Excommunicate 'em. They took upon them to judge of the Controverſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Biſhops; ſuſpended one, and ſet up another; and threaten'd the Refractory with <hi>Deprivation,</hi> if they but diſputed the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of their Summons. Theſe Things they did ſometimes at the Requeſt of the CHURCH, and often with hearty Thanks for what they had done. And thoſe Ages knew no ſuch Thing as diſputing the <hi>competent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> by which they acted, or the <hi>Validity</hi> of their Sentences; ſo long as Nothing was done by them to the Detriment of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith or Religion. This ſhews moſt plainly, that what was practiſed by the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Authority of the Biſhops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2187:36"/> for the firſt three hundred Years, was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> and not in a Claim of any Divine Right to exclude the Secular Powers.</p>
            <p>AND now I come to the</p>
            <p>III. AND laſt Objection. Some are apt to think the Principles I advance too prejudicial to the CHURCH'S Intereſt and Advantage, that they tend too much to oppreſs and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave Her. But I hope, I have not laid my ſelf open deſervedly to any ſuch Charge. I have granted it a divine unalienable Right to the Holy Offices of all Religious Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to the Power of the Keys and to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination. I have allowed it a natural and common Right to all the general Powers of Government, and owned that by Virtue of CHRIST'S Commiſſion, it has a Truſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to it in all its Exigencies; and an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to do every Thing in the Exerciſe of its Spiritual Powers, that is neceſſary to be done for the Propagation and Support of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion. Where then is the Slavery or Oppreſſion in theſe Principles? Or what is it that we can by the Authority of GOD and CHRIST claim more? Other Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Authorities, may be granted to it by the STATE: But of its own Right, I am
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2187:37"/> not convinced that it can pretend to more than theſe.</p>
            <p>I AM, in Truth, very ſenſible, that the Clergy are in ſome Mens Eſteem and Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very low and mean; and I hope, I ſhall alway carry a ready Inclination to do my Endeavour to ſupport both the Honour and the true Intereſt of the Order. But, as all the Contempt that we ſeem to lie under, is either with Men of profligate Principles, and wicked Lives, whoſe Reproaches can do us but little or no Harm; or elſe with thoſe, who take Offence at our Carriage and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct: So Nothing certainly will go farther to raiſe our Character, and promote our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and engage Kings and States to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt us with additional Honours and Powers, than our Prudence and Piety, and Modeſty, and great Humility, which are none of them inconſiſtent with a due Regard to our juſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. And while theſe Virtues and Graces are ſound to ſhine thro' all our Conduct, we may vindicate our real Rights without any Scandal or great Offence. But if we be vain and imprudent in our Behaviour; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome and turbulent in our Conduct, and graſp at Power and Authority in the Church, only to ſupport Factious Parties, and to raiſe Tumults and Seditions againſt the STATE: All
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2187:37"/> this will really do us harm. The Adverſary will not fail to make all the Advantages that they can of it, and we thus give them too juſt a handle thereto. And this which is diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable to the true Temper and Spirit of the Goſpel, will have yet a worſe influence to our mighty Diſadvantage. It will make us cheap and mean in the Eyes of thoſe Wiſe and Good Men, by whoſe deſerved Favour and Intereſt the Dignity and Character of our Holy Order ſhould be ſupported.</p>
            <p>LET any Man of common Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing judge what the World will think or ſay of thoſe Claims and Pretenſions to Divine Power and Authority, which apparently mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter only to Ambition, and Pride, and Faction; but are not at all ſerviceable to the Intereſt of true Religion. Such are the Pretences that I have ſo often mentioned already of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of the Church being <hi>Spiritual Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Lords, Legates,</hi> and <hi>ſupreme Monarchs</hi> in the <hi>Church Regent,</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Church Militant;</hi> and having a Share of CHRIST'S <hi>Kingly Power</hi> in his ſpiritual <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as well as of his Prieſthood. In conſequence of this, to make all Chriſtian Kings, and Princes, and States, their <hi>ſpiritual Inferiors</hi> and <hi>Subjects,</hi> from whom, <hi>Submiſſion</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in all Religious Matters, under the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2187:38"/> of Excommunication, and conſigning them over to the Devil.</p>
            <p>IN the Name of GOD, what Advantage will all this be to Religion? How naturally do ſuch Pretenſions put Mankind upon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring, What Uſe the Clergy have made of this Authority in Times paſt, when they had it in their Hands? And when upon ſeveral Paſſages and Inſtances in Hiſtory, they can tell us, that thro' this very Power, Religion has been depraved and corrupted by the Clergy themſelves, who claim it: What Advantage will this be to the Honour, and Credit, and Reputation of our Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? Will not every notorious Miſcarriage committed under the Covert of <hi>a Divine Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from Chriſt in all Spiritual Cauſes;</hi> occaſion his whole Commiſſion to be evil ſpoken of, and turn the very Name of <hi>divine Right</hi> into Banter and Ridicule, and a Name of Contempt and Deriſion; and give too plauſible a Ground for the ſcandalous Imputation of <hi>Prieſtcraft?</hi> Who muſt bear the Blame of all this? To whom is all this Contempt of the Clergy to be imputed? In too great a Meaſure, to the blameable Arrogance, and boundleſs Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſpiritual Pride of ſome Clergymen. Mankind often fall the lower, by aſpiring too high. The Name of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2187:38"/> always venerable, and treated with great Reſpect among Chriſtians, until ſome began to adore her as a Goddeſs. And Nothing has brought Her to be ſo diſreſpectful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treated, as the Idolatry of Men in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping her. And ſo I in my Conſcience believe, That where there has been no ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Immorality of Life, Nothing has made our Sacred Order meaner, or lower in their Intereſt and Eſteem, than the claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under GOD and CHRIST more Power than They ever intended to beſtow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us.</p>
            <p>AND eſpecially <hi>then</hi> are theſe Pretences ſcandalous and diſadvantageous to our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, <hi>when</hi> the ſpiritual Authority of the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> is ſet up in Oppoſition to the STATE; and made uſe of as a Check upon the Secular Powers, and a Means to weaken them in their Authority, and to cramp them in the Adminiſtration of Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I verily believe, that the Chriſtian CHURCH has loſt more of Her true Intereſt by this, than by any other Means whatſoever. In that when the Lay Powers recover themſelves out of ſuch injurious Oppreſſions, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail to make very large and ample Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſals. And here, I muſt beg leave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, That this Claim of an <hi>Independent</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:2187:39"/> 
               <hi>Power</hi> in Eccleſiaſtical and Spiritual Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, has not, that I know of been ſet up by any of the Clergy of our <hi>Reformed</hi> CHURCH from Her firſt Reformation untill the late Happy Revolution. And as it was then firſt ſet on foot by the <hi>Non-jurors</hi> in Defence of the Deprived Biſhops and in Oppoſition to King WILLIAM and his Government: So has it ever ſince been chiefly held up by thoſe who have had little or no Affection for our National Eſtabliſhment and Conſtitution from that Time. And the Scandalous Part of all this Scuffle in Controverſy, and a Schiſmatical Separation from our CHURCH, is not made on the Account of our Holy Religion, and in Defence of the Powers by which that is to be Preſerved; but only in Behalf of a few particular Men, and by thoſe who are confeſſedly in the Intereſt of the <hi>Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and who have Nothing more at Heart then this groundleſs and unreaſonable Schiſm in the CHURCH to diſpoſe the Hearts of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> People to another Rebellion againſt the STATE. Had it not been for the ſervicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of this Doctrine to breed ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions among us, and to throw us into Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſeditions, it had never been ſet on Foot at firſt. And if all other Methods of ſerving and ſupporting the <hi>Pretender's</hi> Cauſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2187:39"/> had not been baffled and made ineffectual, it had never been revived now. For while they had Hope from other Means, Theſe were laid aſleep. And if Men were not blinded and infatuated above all Meaſure: This is Demonſtration clear enough, that no ſuch Eccleſiaſtical Power can be given by GOD and CHRIST. The foremention'd Conceſſion of our Adverſaries being a moſt certain and indiſputable Truth: <hi>That Chriſt has given no Authority to his Church, that can interfere with the Civil Powers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To make an end; I think I have plainly and clearly proved, that altho' by CHRIST'S Commiſſion the Divine Offices of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religious Miniſtrations are Appropriated to the Biſhops and Clergy only: Yet the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Governing Powers of this Divine So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety are not. That as theſe belong to it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of that <hi>Common Right</hi> which naturally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to all Societies, and as they are <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the Attainment of that End for which it was Inſtituted of GOD; ſo conſequently they have nothing in 'em to exclude the Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of temporal Governors. Becauſe thoſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Governors have the very ſame natural and common Right over all their Subjects, and in all Caſes and Cauſes, to do every Thing that ſhall be found neceſſary to the Support
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2187:40"/> and Preſervation of the STATE; which the others can pretend to Claim for the Support and Preſervation of the CHURCH. Nay far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That it would be no certain Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to Religion for the CHURCH to be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd of ſuch Authority. That it would rob Kings and Princes of one great Branch of their Sovereignty; and may be, and often has been, uſed to defeat even their Civil Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations and to ſhake their Thrones, and to Ruin their Dominions. And in a Word that ſuch an Independent Authority is Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible with the Supremacy of Secular Princes, whoſe Affairs muſt inevitably be influenced and controul'd thereby. Therefore too ſuch inconſiſtent Supremacies cannot be believed to be derived both from GOD.</p>
            <p>IN Conſequence of all this, I have ſhew'd, That Princes have an Authority both in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and alſo in the Deprivation of Biſhops, if they be diſloyal and diſaffected to them. That without ſuch a Power, Government may be made too weak to ſubſiſt, and may be in Danger of being Overturned by the Power of the Clergy. That as this is what Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion never was intended for, ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all ſuch Deprivations made by the legal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the STATE are good and <hi>Valid</hi> to all Intents and Purpoſes, and oblige the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of all the Subjects.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:2187:40"/>
            <p> THE Concluſion of all this is, That the Deprivation of the late <hi>Non-juring</hi> Biſhops was in all reſpects <hi>Valid;</hi> that the People of their ſeveral Sees are thereby diſcharged from all Submiſſion, and Duty, and ſpiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and Relation to them. That they have no longer any lawful Authority in our CHURCH; but we as Chriſtians are bound to adhere to the Religious Communion of thoſe whom the King by the Laws of the Land ſhall Promote into their Places. And in a Word, that the contrary Practice in leaving the Communion of this eſtabliſhed CHURCH, and ſetting up Religious Aſſemblies under the pretended Authority of ſuch Deprived Biſhops or their Adherents: Is very Wicked and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the Sight of GOD, and an undoubted Schiſm from the Communion of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I WILL only add, that as theſe have been the conſtant Doctrines and Principles of the <hi>Church of England</hi> from the Beginning of the Reformation down to our Times: So they had not now been diſputed had it not been in favour of the <hi>Pretender</hi> and of <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2187:41"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>THE</hi> Occaſion and Importance of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>page</hi> 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The State has a ſupremacy in all Caſes ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedently to the Church's Claim,</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Natural Religion gives no Independent Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the Prieſthood,</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chriſts Commiſſion appropriates only the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration in Holy Offices,</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The General Governing Powers of the Church, founded only on Common Right, and not Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to the Clergy by Chriſt's Commiſſion,</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Therefore not to be Executed by an Authority In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent on the State. This proved by Six Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments,</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>I.</hi> From the nature of the Powers in Diſpute,</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Where Chriſt has not appropriated the Power, the State is not excluded,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi> admits this in Part,</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>How the Church's pretended Independency, is to be underſtood,</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2187:41"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Practices of the three firſt Centuries were of mere Neceſſity,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Royal Preiſthood Nothing to this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy,</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The <hi>Non-jurors</hi> lofty Style and Pretenſions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable to the Temper of the Goſpel,</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Church's real Authority muſt not be judg'd of by high Strains and Metaphors; but by the Powers actually convey'd and appropriated,</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>II.</hi> Such an Independency in the Church not conſiſtent with the Subordination of Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to that of the Father,</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>III.</hi> Not at all Serviceable to Religion,</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>IV.</hi> It robs Secular Powers of one Branch of their Sovereignty,</cell>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>That ſecular Princes and States have Authority in Matters of Religion, proved from the Jewiſh Kings,</cell>
                     <cell>31, 32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>V.</hi> Such a Claim dangerous to all Kingdoms, as Weakening and Ruining their Authority in their Temporal Affairs,</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>This Evidenced by the Practices of the <hi>Non-juring Schiſmaticks,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>VI.</hi> Two Independent Powers in the Government
<pb facs="tcp:2187:42"/> of the ſame Body of Men breeds inevitable Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and therefore cannot be of <hi>GOD,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Neceſſity of granting, that Chriſt has given the Church no Authority that interferes with Civil Powers,</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The State muſt have as ample a Power for its own Preſervation, as the Church has for Hers,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>This neceſſarily gives them an Authority.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. In the Election of Biſhops and Clergymen,</cell>
                     <cell>44.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. In their Deprivation,</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>No Perſecution in depriving the Nonjuring Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>No real Invaſion of Eccleſiaſtical Authority.</cell>
                     <cell>53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Three Objections anſwered; ſhewing,</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>I. That the Relation of a Biſhop to his Flock is not Divine, or Unalienable,</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>II. The Principles and Practices of the Cypria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Age, altogether foreign to this Controverſy,</cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>III. No real Detriment to the Chriſtian Church or Prieſthood from the Principles of this Eſſay.</cell>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The propereſt Method of Advancing the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter and Intereſt of the Clergy.</cell>
                     <cell>70</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>The Concluſion.</cell>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 14. <hi>line</hi> 21. <hi>read</hi> Modification. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> Powers. <hi>p.</hi> 50. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>for</hi> their <hi>r.</hi> the.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2187:42"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
